48-year-old Ash came to see me with a
chief complaint of fatigue weight gain
around the abdomen the waist and her
hips in fact Ashley realized that her
weight continuously increased for the
past two years and she couldn't lose it
she didn't know why it was happening
where the weight was coming from and why
it was so difficult to get rid of she
also had type 2 diabetes and she recalls
when she was in her early 30s she was di
pre-diabetic but her doctor told her she
was
fine her blood sugars currently as a
type 2 diabetic would range anywhere
between 300 to 400 fasting in the
morning she was quite disturbed by
this she didn't understand why her blood
sugars were so high even while she was
taking
medication are you like Ashley you have
type 2 diabetes or you know someone who
suffers from type 2 diabetes and it's
not being properly managed Ashley wished
her doctor told her that when she was a
pre-diabetic that she was already
experiencing damage to her eyes her
nerves her blood vessels and her kidneys
before her diabetes diagnosis
more than 37 million people in the
United States are diagnosed with type 2
diabetes and one and five don't know
they have it type 2 diabetes accounts
for
approximately 90 to
95% of all diagnosed
cases while these statistics might sound
alarming I have good news for
you type two diabetes is mainly driven
by lifestyle and environmental
factors welcome to True help Tuesday I'm
Dr Kenisha Reynolds a licensed
naturopathic functional medicine
physician former molecular biologist and
CSI forensic
scientist if you're like Ashley
suffering from type 2 diabetes and you
can't seem to get your blood sugars
within normal ranges stay tune today
we're going to cover some things that
you can do to get better glycemic
control nutrition is really important
it's the Cornerstone of our
health food is our medicine food impacts
our physiology at a fundamental
level so for type two diabetes the most
important things that you have to do in
terms of nutrition is number one avoid
all inflammatory foods such as
inflammatory fats that most mostly come
from animal saturated fat refined sugar
carbohydrates very
refin processed foods and food additives
and artificial ingredients when you
remove these inflammatory foods your
body has an opportunity to heal itself
you want to replace these inflammatory
foods with healthy foods nutrient-dense
Foods plant-based diets confer a 78%
reduction risk in type 2 diabetes and
56% reduction in metabolic
syndrome when you're putting your plate
together there are four important food
elements that you want to focus on when
you get adequate protein in the diet it
helps to reduce Cravings which is
another reason why people have type 2
diabetes number two focus on slow
burning resist in
starch these foods are found in our
beans and
legumes if you aim to get 15 to 60 grams
of resistant starch per day it's been
shown to lower insulin levels post meals
and increase insulin
sensitivity you want to focus
on as you're focusing on removing
the the toxic fat from the diet you want
to replace it with healthy fats those
tend to be found in your nuts in your
seeds and making sure that you're
getting olives and avocado healthy
sources of
fat another important food element to
focus on number four is
fiber because fiber helps to slow down
glucose absorption and a small
intestine the other important feature of
fiber which is fantastic is that it
moves more slowly throughout the
gastrointestinal system keeping us full
longer that prevents the need to eat
excessive calories and it helps to
reduce Cravings so the more fiber you
include in a diet it will lower your
need for excess calories you can avoid
weight gain this way and it helps to
better stabilize blood sugar another
feature of fiber is that it helps to
stabilize our lipids it helps to reduce
the LDL
cholesterol if you're a person who has
elevated LDL
cholesterol fiber also provides a
beneficial substrate for the microbiome
and we're going to also talk about the
role to microbiome plays in regulating
blood
sugar the aforementioned foods are
really important animportant for
managing blood sugar and as soon as you
avoid those inflammatory foods and
replace them with primarily plant-based
Foods you'll see better glycemic
control another important feature of a
plant-based diet is that it's loaded
with nutrients it's a nutrient dense
diet it will provide you adequate
nutrients that play a role in glycemic
control nut nut deficiencies and
nutrient insufficiencies can also play a
role in type 2 diabetes this is another
reason why the diet is incredibly
important for maintaining proper blood
sugar levels vitamin D
zinc
chromium and inositol
deficiencies have been connected to type
2 diabetes vitamin D plays a role in
regulating insulin release from the
pancreas vitamin D supplementation if
there's a vitamin D deficiency can
improve glycemic
levels various nutrient deficiencies or
insufficiencies can increase the risk
for type 2
diabetes vitamin D
aocl and certain micronutrients such as
zinc chromium and magnesium all of these
nutrients play a very important role in
maintaining and managing healthy blood
sugar levels
because they either indirectly or
directly influence the release of
insulin from the
pancreas we have to remember
fundamentally that a lot of biochemical
processes that happen in our body are
nutrient dependent that means there are
a lot of nutrients that these
biochemical Pathways require in order to
perform their task and their enzymes
that play a vital role and being able to
properly manage manage glucose so in
order to get proper blood sugar levels
and to manage these blood sugar we want
to make sure that the nutrients are
available and so a very easy way to in
addition to the food elements that you
want to make sure that you get in your
diet and have it on your plate want to
make sure that you're getting different
colors and aim anywhere between four to
five colors her meal so that at the end
of the day you're eating of the rainbow
because all of these Foods plants have
nutrients that can influence blood
sugar another element of nutrition is
not only the quality of what you eat but
the meal timing if you want to get
better blood sugar balance it's really
important to avoid eating four to 5
hours before bed the reason being when
when it's time for bed when we lay down
to sleep the stomach should be empty
your body should be resting it should be
fasting it shouldn't be focused on
digestion 30% of energy goes into
digestion and if you're going to sleep
at night with a full stomach and you're
lying down you're not sitting upright
okay sitting upright allows for Gravity
to help support pushing that food down
in a stomach so that it Digest gestion
can happen digestion is impacted when
we're lying down on our back with food
in the stomach and this impacts the
quality and efficiency of digestion and
this can imp impact our blood
sugar we want to make sure to maximize
proper glucose metabolism we want to
make sure that we're allowing the
stomach to rest digestion slows down in
the evening your digestive system as
well as many other systems are on the
circadium Rhythm metabolism is at its
highest in the early part of the day
insulin sensitivity is highest in the
early part of the day why not take
advantage of your natural ability to
digest your food and have good lipid and
glucose metabolism during the early
parts of the day make meals smaller in
the evening and avoid eating too late at
night because all of this impacts your
glucose your body's ability to properly
break down your fats and your
sugars and the very last thing you want
to consider is fasten interventions
fasten interventions can promote
beneficial effects on our
metabolism take for example the fast and
mimikin diet fast and mimikin diet has
been shown in to improve markers of
insulin
resistance and support weight weight
loss periodic fasting has been shown to
be very therapeutic and stabilizing
blood
sugar in one study the fast and
mimicking diet was shown to improve
markers of insulin resistance suggesting
that periodic fasting can be very
beneficial for type 2
diabetes but if you're considering
fasting always talk to your doctor
before starting any new supplement or
any diet uh
prescription but fasting is definitely
something I found clinically to be quite
effective for patients suffering from
type 2 diabetes so in
summary be sure to focus your nutrition
on nutrient density foods that will
provide adequate nutrients
fiber
Protein healthy fats and slow burning
resistant
starch avoid eating late night meals
avoid skipping
meals and avoid meals four to 5 hours
before
bedtime
lastly consider fasten interventions for
glycemic control it works lovely and
I've seen it it works so lovely for
balancing blood
sugar be sure to give a thumb thumbs up
if found this video helpful and be sure
to share it with anyone you know
suffering from blood sugar issues thank
you for joining us on true Health
Tuesday